And now the film…
Jesus Christ Superstar is a drama, history film directed by Norman Jewison.
As played out by a theatre troupe, the last days of Jesus Christ are
depicted from the perspective of Judas Iscariot, his betrayer.
As Jesus' following increases, Judas begins to worry that Jesus is falling for his own hype, forgetting
the principles of his teachings and growing too close to the prostitute Mary Magdalene.
Jesus Christ, played by Ted Neeley.
Judas Iscariot, played by Carl Anderson.
Mary Magdalene, played by Yvonne Elliman.
Pontius Pilate, played by Barry Dennen.
Caiaphas, played by Bob Bingham.
Simon Zealotes, played by Larry Marshall.
Jesus Christ Superstar is a 1973 American musical Biblical drama film directed by Norman
Jewison, co-written by Jewison and Melvyn Bragg, and choreographed by Robert Iscove.
It is based on the 1970 concept album written by Tim Rice and composed by
Andrew Lloyd Webber, which in turn spawned the 1971 stage musical.
The film depicts the conflict between Judas and Jesus and the emotions and motivations
of the main characters during the week of the crucifixion of Jesus.
It stars Ted Neeley, Carl Anderson, Yvonne Elliman and
Barry Dennen in the principal roles.
Jesus Christ Superstar premiered at the Uptown Theater in Washington D.C.
on June 26, 1973, and was released theatrically in
the United States on August 15, 1973.
Despite criticism from a few religious groups and mixed reviews
from critics, the film was a box office success.
Neeley, Anderson, and Elliman were nominated for Golden Globe Awards in 1974, for
their portrayals of Jesus, Judas, and Mary Magdalene, respectively.
The film was also nominated for Best Motion Picture – Musical or
Comedy, and received an Oscar nomination for Best Score.
The film explores themes of dance, israel, christianity, crucifixion, musical.
The tone is emotional.